all right hello and welcome everyone
this is active bookstream number 2.0
we are going to be discussing the
textbook active inference the free
energy principle in mind brain and
behavior 2022 textbook by Thomas Parr
Giovanni pizzullo and Carl friston
in this live stream with Ali and I we're
going to be giving some overviews and
some kind of points that you'll want to
have in mind a little bit of background
in context specifically on chapters one
two three and six we're going to do more
live streams in the future that will
cover the other chapters there's 10
chapters overall and the goal of this
live stream is to use the live stream
format to produce materials that we can
then clip out so that the textbook
groups which we have multiple ongoing
cohorts at The Institute so that those
textbook groups can be really engaging
and discussion oriented because after
several cohorts of going through this
Ali and I and others have started to
kind of hone our understanding of the
textbook and so we are starting to feel
ready to put down some background in
context.0 video
and then ideally people who are
participating in the textbook group
cohorts will be able to view and think
about those videos leading up to a
discussion so that when we do have the
discussions in the textbook group that
those can be maximally interactive and
engaging so before we jump into chapter
one Ali do you want to just add anything
about uh the textbook or anything else
hello I'm Ali I'm very happy and excited
to be here uh to discuss the book that
we've fallen in love for the last year
and despite the fact that we've been
studying and discussing this book for
more than a year uh there's still a lot
to learn and unpack so yeah great
all right so then we will begin in just
a few seconds
the chapter one and overview
all right this section is going to be
the chapter one and overview of the
active inference textbook
so shown here are the table of contents
there are 10 chapters and three
appendices in this book and they're
separated into part one with chapters
one through five and part two chapters
six through ten Ali do you want to give
any overview thoughts on the
organization or structure of the book
okay so
um
uh can you hear me now sorry yes okay so
part one is basically uh more line
um in terms of the theoretical
construction of the
active inference and it provides some uh
conceptual and theoretical uh tools to
be utilized in the second part uh
because uh for the second part we're
mostly we mostly deal with the Practical
side of active inference how to actually
Implement active inference to model uh
some of the systems of Interest so
that's basically the main justification
behind dividing up these chapters into
two
great all right we're going to pass over
the short preface written by Carl
friston but it's worth a read it's only
several pages long so let's go to
chapter one overview so do you have any
opening thoughts on chapter one or where
does one even begin with such a book
sure uh yeah for chapter one I think uh
probably the most central theme of
chapter one is uh about the two
different approaches to active inference
namely the high road and the low road uh
and I think it provides a really nice
perspective to view a kind of a whole
picture and how the different components
of active inference fit together
so but um also I I highly recommend uh
chapter 13 from this book Andy Clark and
it's and Andy Clark and his critics uh
written by
chapter 13 I think is entitled beyond
the desert landscape written by Carl
Preston in which he provides a more
elaborate and a bit philosophical
reasoning behind uh what exactly are low
roads and high road and what are the
aims of each approach and the
distinction between those two so
um for uh chapter one we begin obviously
with um an introductory paragraph which
sets the stage for uh the I mean all the
components that would be discussed in
this chapter so but a very important uh
section I believe is a section two here
which is how do living organisms persist
and act adaptively which is basically
the main question active inference is
trying to address uh so if we want to uh
describe active inference in uh I mean
minimalistically with only one sentence
or two uh probably we can say something
to the effect that uh it's a theory that
address this very question here
so I why they've opened up this chapter
with the important
question and then action three
which is again a continuation of section
one but a bit more specifically about
active inference and how active
inference is
addressing the question
provided in the section two so
basically again active inference is a
modeling framework for modeling the
behaviors from first principles and
what is meant by first principles will
be elaborated upon in the following
chapters and the following sections and
also I'll be using the following
chapters
but very briefly it's a kind of modeling
framework that tries to somehow
use a variational principles such as
free energy principle to uh to construct
modeling and mathematical tools that
would enable us to uh
to describe a dynamical systems of
living and even non-living agents in
terms of those variational principles
and how those agents or those systems
are coupled with their environment
so that's basically the
unificatory principle that is at the
heart of this active inference approach
because uh yes exactly here
it's a kind of description of this
action perception Loop that is at the
heart of active inference or fep
framework
and then we go to
chapter sorry section 1.4 which is again
a description of the structure of the
book and why those two parts are divided
as such
so as I said earlier first part is more
uh concerned with the theoretical
underpinnings of active inference and
the second part is more about the
Practical side of it as we see in these
subsection headings here
so that's uh
yeah and then
a very important diagram
which will provide very helpful as we
whole book is provided in figure 1.2
which kind of uh
ties all the different strands of
various related theories such as
predictive coding predictive processing
Bayesian brain hypothesis and so on into
a kind of unified and integrated
framework by using those two
trajectories of
constructing active inference namely the
high road and the low road
so it literally here is represented as
the high road and the low road in this
diagram
uh so very briefly uh
high road is a kind of top down approach
to active in Prince it begins with the
question
how and how things should act if they
exist in other words if they persist
through time sorry in other words
it kind of sets sets the stage for
developing the concept of markup
blankets
uh and then uh obviously with by uh
setting then also
um surprise minimization
uh it attempts to
elaborate that
um Road by adding other aspects of
modeling other aspects of theory such as
predictive processing self-evidencing
auto-poiesis and so on and then reach an
integrated version of active inference
which is basically an integration
between perception and action so uh
I believe the main thing that sets
active inference apart from all the
other related theories such as
predictive processing and predictive
coding is the very in deep integration
of action and perception so action is
not just
um some afterthought or some additional
component that needs to be accounted for
it is deeply woven into the fabric of
the theory so as we'll see especially in
chapters two and three
even the mathematical formalism for
perception and action
are interestingly similar to each other
and even symmetric and it shows that uh
perception and action are actually not
uh separate and distinct totally
distinct entities and Concepts and
um active inference uh definitely
provides a very promising framework to
integrate them into a holistic framework
and another approach to construct that
same theory is to begin with the
probabilistic description uh a base
theorem and
um try to build up
the formalism of active inference using
uh Bayes inference theorem theorem and
Bayesian statistical inference so again
we hear a system
very
I mean apparently different and distinct
strands such as predictive coding basing
brain hypothesis and so on but as we see
all of those different strands can be
United and tied together with within
this low road approach to active
inference
so
um
I guess that's uh I'll just give one
short thought thanks these are great
yeah just one short thought thank you
Ali for these great summaries
the low road and the high road are going
to be explored in a lot more detail in
the coming chapters two and three
we can think of the high road as being a
y
because it describes how persistent or
re-measurable systems exist now they
might be using base theorem or they
might be using any other kind of
mechanism internally but the high road
is describing the why of existence
from the low road the bottom-up approach
is kind of like a how you could use
Bayes theorem to describe persistent
Auto poetic entities
or you could use Bayes theorem for other
purposes too so where these two roads
intersect is active inference and we
have a lot more discussion coming and of
course unpacked in the textbook groups
about how these really map on to bottom
up and top-down causation and the
plurality of y's that we approach in
different settings
good to continue
yes sure
some of the coming sections uh of this
chapter continuing from page eight are
going to describe what are happening in
the next chapters so chapter two is
going to set out the low road
perspective
chapter 3 is going to describe the high
road chapter four we will unpack active
inference more formally that's one of
the math heavy chapters
chapter 5 will move from formal
treatments to biological implications of
active inference with a special focus on
mammalian neurophysiology
chapter 5 sets out the process Theory
associated with active inference and
gives a lot of Hands-On and empirical
examples and that's a lot of the first
part of the book
they're then going to summarize some of
the key points and distillations from
that theory heavy first section one of
them is that as Ali mentioned perception
and action are complementary processes
and ways that fulfill the same
imperative free energy minimization we
sometimes summarize that by saying that
in the pursuit of the minimization of
free energy agents can either change
their mind or change the world change
your mind is associated with perception
and learning
and those are distinguished later
and changing the world is associated
with action
there's some discussion about action
selection and optimal policy selection
and all cognitive operations in active
inference are conceptualized as
inference over generative models so the
true kernel the cognitive kernel of
active inference is going to be the
generative model
want to pick up from here or give any
thoughts on generative models and then
carry on thanks Ali
just one point is uh there is a common
misconception about generative models
which is that a generative models only
refers to this the interstates of the
system and also its markup blanket but
actually generative model kind of
Encompass all the states of interest
of the situation we're trying to model
so it also encodes the problem the
probabilistic information about the
external States as well so generative
model can be thought of as a kind of
the whole state of the system and by
System here I mean uh the coupled and
the couple says um a couple Dynamics
between the internal and external States
so uh that might be helpful to keep in
mind in the book
great one other distinction that comes
up and is used a lot nowadays although
it's not always used in Prior literature
is the distinction between the
generative model and the generative
process we're going to come back to it
but usually
the generative model is being used to
describe our statistical model of the
agent of interest and the generative
process is the process that generates
observations that are then passed to the
generative model as observations however
because generative models can be
generative processes for each other
these two are not necessarily distinct
in principle so in different simulations
and in different specific cases
generative models can also be generative
processes for each other that leads us
towards talking about ecosystems of
shared intelligence and interactions
amongst generative models but when we're
talking about generative model it's like
the organism or the system of interest
that we're focused on
there are some more uh themes that arise
from the first half of the book now
we're on page 11. action is
quintessentially goal directed and
purposes of we talk a lot about how
preference plays a role in shaping
action selection and active inference
and the goal-directed nature of active
inference will be unpacked in chapters
two and three
they discuss how various constructs of
active inference have plausible
biological analogs in the brain
once one has defined a specific
generative model for a problem at hand
one can move from active inference as a
normative Theory to active inference as
a process Theory which makes specific
empirical predictions and there's many
many interesting philosophy of science
type discussions that we have about
explain predict design control
and then we get to section 1.4.2 giving
overview on part two active inference in
practice
so I'll just continue on chapter 6 is
going to introduce a recipe for building
active inference models so this is where
the step-by-step comes into play it's
going to give a sequence of of steps and
approaches that you can take to go from
understanding the structural aspects of
a system or phenomena of interest and
build your way towards having an active
inference model that can then be
implemented in code and we have various
examples and we're there in the textbook
group to work with everyone who wants to
take this journey but chapter six is
going to describe that process of
building the active inference generative
model so that's a recipe chapter and
there's a lot more that goes into the
restaurant also as we kind of have fun
exploring
chapter 7 and 8 are like a pair and they
describe two different broad families of
generative models now these two families
of generative models they work well they
play well with each other but they are a
very educationally relevant to also
consider separately chapter seven is
going to focus on the discrete time
generative model
and chapter 8 is going to focus on the
continuous time generative models and
again these discrete and continuous time
models can be nested and interoperable
however they do describe some very
important different situations and so
chapter seven and eight have a lot of
technical information on the discrete
and continuous time formulations of
active inference and also about how they
integrate together
chapter 9 is illustrations of how active
inference models can be used to analyze
data from behavioral experiments and so
this kind of goes beyond chapter six's
recipe and it talks about some of the
process of making a behavioral
experiment and then using the outcomes
of that behavioral experiment the data
from that experiment and using that to
parameterize and do statistics with the
active inference generative model
and chapter 10 brings it all together
chapter 10 is a lot like chapter one and
we've even joked of reading the book
backwards that's how great chapter 10 is
so for those who are reading chapter one
consider reading chapter 10 next and
then picking back up with chapter two
because chapter 10 is going to give some
judgments and also sketch some exciting
future directions for where active
inference is in relationship to other
fields and where it's going
so I also second that yeah
uh the second part of the book
illustrates a broad variety of models of
biological and cognitive phenomena so
it's an application oriented second half
of the book and we have a lot of
accessory code and approaches and
notebooks so one may not find that this
is the One-Stop shop that they were
looking for however for those who dive
in there's absolutely more than enough
to scaffold their Learning Journey
um and then section 1.5 is the summary
the chapter introduces the active
inference approach to explain biological
problems from a normative perspective
and preview some implications of this
perspective that will be unpacked in
later chapters
it describes the structural outline of
the book chapters one through five being
Theory chapter 6 through 10 being
practice
and then it signals that the next two
chapters are going to develop the low
and the high road perspectives
and all together
that is chapter one any other thoughts
on chapter one
uh not specifically but I think it
provides a really good context to uh the
rest of the book in terms of how all the
different elements of active imprints
comes into play in addressing uh
different
problems different problems
awesome
on to chapter two the low road to active
inference so all chapters begin with a
short quotation and the quotation here
reads my thinking is first and last and
always for the sake of my doing William
James so even before reading the chapter
these quotations are often great places
to jump off and have a discussion so Ali
please begin and go as long as you want
on the low road to active inference
okay
so I guess
chapter two uh as the title suggests
um it's the construction of active
inference Theory uh from the Viewpoint
of uh of the low road active inference
so uh it begins by uh providing this
notion of perception as inference
because uh more often than not we
usually think of perception as something
uh just in a computational sense of the
sense is the processing of the of the
inputs or rather it's the raw processing
of the inputs but here it shows that it
can also be described as or even more
accurately described as a kind of
inference so it's not just a simple and
raw processing of the inputs as my uh a
computational model uh
or a computer analogy might suggest it's
more
um like something that we predict and
then
um then we compare our inputs or the
inputs we get from the stimuli uh with
our prediction and then try to somehow
minimize that prediction error so I
believe that this notion of perception
is inference is uh the most Central
notion of all the related theories of
predictive coding predictive processing
Bayesian brain hypothesis so up to now
active inference uh is not very
different from all the other theories
it's basically a subset or a variant of
those theories but then it progresses uh
into uh distinguishing uh distinguishing
the active active inference from all the
other theories and how uh it stands
apart from the other ones
uh so uh in section 2.1
uh we began with some of the basics of
probability Theory namely the base
theorem uh in box 2.1 uh and uh some
simple examples uh about how base
theorem can be applied
uh and again a very important uh page or
important part of this section will be
page 20 which describes the concept of
surprisal and specifically the
statistical surprisal and how it differs
from the phenomenological surprise or
psychological surprise uh so uh and
that's how we can formulate the
statistical surprise yes yes just just
to catch up here this example that's
going to come back again and again is a
person who's guessing the object that's
in their hand and it could be a frog or
an apple and the object is going to jump
or not and so that's used as a way to
talk about the Bayesian updating that
forms the kernel of a variety of
Bayesian brain like models including
active inference
and then
um there are the presentation of the
exact base so in simple cases you can
compute exactly what you want with Bayes
theorem however it's a lot more
effective on large data sets to use
certain approximations and heuristics
that we're going to be discussing
and then
um Ali has highlighted that there are
two concepts that are very closely
related to each other regarding surprise
there's Surprise by itself and then
there's Bayesian surprise so please pick
up there what are surprise and Bayesian
surprise and why do they matter here
yes so um well surprise I mean the
regular surprise as we're all familiar
with uh is something
um more related to our sense of surprise
or psychological sense of surprise of uh
observing some unexpected phenomena or
unexpected Behavior but Bayesian
surprise or statistical surprise uh is
the of course closely related with the
psychological sense of surprise but a
bit more rigorous in which it's a way to
compare uh to probabilistic information
using a callback Library Divergence and
somehow getting the I mean how
unexpected that information
emerging from callback Divergence uh and
they call it the surprisal so uh
surprisal is uh you know in other words
is a way to formulating those unexpected
uh probabilistic information and it
doesn't necessarily uh align or maps
onto perfectly are psychological sense
of surprisal but as I said it's closely
related with that
I know I was just gonna say that
um
I was just going to say that by surprise
um almost in the rest all the
um other sections and chapters of the
book uh we basically mean this Bayesian
surprise uh sense of the world and in
order to distinguish that with the
regular sense of surprise uh sometimes
in the literature surprisal is used to
refer to Bayesian surprise
yes so they're both measured in
information theoretic units this is all
happening in information geometric
spaces the first concepts of surprise is
applied to a given single observations
how surprising is that one observation
and so in that sense it's a lot like the
z-score of a data point coming in with
respect to a statistical distribution so
it's like you have a height distribution
in a classroom and you measure one
person and then you can say what is the
z-score of that measurement was it right
at the center of the distribution with
the z-score of zero or with a two
standard deviations higher with a
z-score of two so it's kind of like that
and that's why there's a discussion of
probability distributions and their
support which is the X values for which
they're defined and surprise function
with the fancy I and that's going to be
a function that helps you compute how
surprising each observation is given a
parameter as of that distribution
whereas this Bayesian surprise
is more related to learning it has to do
with how much updating happens between
the prior and the posterior and that's
before and after the observation so one
could imagine a surprising observation
surprise concept one that either does or
doesn't update the prior into a very
different posterior so as Ali mentioned
they are not exactly the same but it's
going to be important to understand how
they're different and that's worked out
again in the case of the Apple jumping
box 2.2 continues with a discussion of
expectations now expectation in everyday
parlance might be specifically referring
to something in the future like I expect
it to rain tomorrow
and in statistics when we talk about the
expectation we're talking about the
weighted average or the center of
gravity of a distribution and that can
be in both a discrete distribution at
which point you have a weighted sum or a
continuous distribution in which case
it's an integral so you can have an
expectation for the humidity tomorrow
and so that might refer to the center of
gravity at A T equals plus one but just
taking a loan expectation means center
of gravity of a statistical distribution
not anticipation
section 2.3 is going to describe how
some of this how this low road that
we're on is going to connect to
biological inference
there's uh more discussion of the
generative model and the generative
process
and a little bit of a hint that the
generative model captures aspects of the
generative process which is where we see
a lot of the classical cybernetic
theorems and Concepts like requisite
diversity good regulator theorem and so
on however the generative model does not
have to be exactly isomorphic with the
generative process for example
degenerative process the temperature in
the room might be a continuous variable
but then the generative model might be
discrete only modeling integer based
temperatures or might be categorical
like too hot just right and too cold so
there's a lot of articulations that can
be done because of how flexible and
interoperable generative models are with
each other
vicar 2.2 is going to expand upon that
chapter 1 representation of the
cybernetic action perception Loop and
we're going to see this more in terms of
a generative model and generative
process articulation and there are
incoming speaking from the perspective
of the generative model the agent
they're incoming and outgoing
dependencies in this graph and this is a
little bit like a schema more so than a
formal graph but also it is like a
Bayesian graph where nodes are variables
and edges are causal relationships and
so we have the internal states of the
model
the external states of the generative
process and then the blanket states that
make internal and external States
conditionally independent and again
speaking from the perspective of the
agent although there is a symmetry we
can talk about the incoming sensory
signals happening from the observations
handed from the process passed on to the
internal states of the generative model
and then the outgoing actions that are
selected that then can influence the
hidden state of the world for example
going and turning on the heater to
increase the temperature in the room
and so this action perception Loop or
particular partition is going to get
explored in a lot more detail in the
coming sections
previous section 2.3 was on perception
as inference and now action as inference
is going to be discussed and that is
where they say the discussion to this
point is common to all Bayesian brain
theories
we now introduce the simple but
fundamental Advance offered by octave
inference which is the extension of this
inferential perspective to consideration
of action as inference
perception action cooperate to realize a
single objective
section 2.5 is about minimizing the
discrepancy between the model and the
world we already described that there's
two ways for this to happen change your
mind and change the world that's how the
discrepancy can be reduced or managed
we see a variant of the action
perception Loop where the agent is
making perceptions uh predictive
models of the world
that through perception are being
juxtaposed with observations handed from
the generative process the world and a
discrepancy is realized some non-zero
discrepancy
and then here are those two paths to
minimize free energy change beliefs by
perception and learning or change the
world through action
section 2.6 is going to discuss how the
exact Bayesian approach described
earlier is absolutely spot on if you
have infinite Computing resources
however we're often interested in Rapid
or large data sets where we want to be
able to get approximate Bayesian
computation or probably approximately
correct computation in a vastly
accelerated fashion and so that is going
to be approached using what's called
variational Bayesian inference that's
unpacked in chapter four
but it suffices to say that variational
Bayesian inference implies substituting
two intractable quantities
the posterior probability and log model
evidence
with two quantities that approximate
them but can be computed efficiently the
approximate posterior q and a
variational free energy so it transforms
an intractable estimation problem into a
highly tractable optimization problem
pick up from there Ali
uh yes but sorry I just wanted to point
out out a couple of things especially
about section 2.3 because I believe it
is um one of the crucial sections of
this chapter and in fact the whole book
because uh it provides some of the
justifications of using uh Bayesian
inference uh as opposed to as some other
uh
mathematical techniques such as maximum
likelihood estimation but
more important than that I think it's
this concept of optimality which comes
into play in almost everywhere in the
literature and of course in this book so
there are actually two Notions of
optimality which is not discussed in
detail here namely Bayesian optimality
and Jane's optimality but uh some in
some of the recent papers and Bayesian
mechanics uh Dalton's active development
and others have shown that those two
concepts of optimality are actually
congruent with each other so that's one
of the reasons
that the Duality between
fep free energy principle and
constrained maximum entropy principle
um
I can
I mean it's one of the justifications
for uh providing that dual formalism
between those two uh so uh but another
point I wanted to mention here is
because I've seen that using uh the word
hidden State uh can be a bit confusing
for some people because uh when we
observe uh something as an observation
obviously it is not quote-unquote hidden
right so what a hidden State here refers
to is actually the hidden cause of that
observation so it's not that the
observation itself is hidden from the
observational or it's unobserved so that
might be a bit uh confusing uh if if we
don't take into consideration the exact
meaning of the Hidden state or latent
State here and in the rest of the
literature
so continuing from section 2.6 uh here
we see uh one of the two Central
equations of active inference which is
equation 2.5
for variational free energy so uh it's
as I said I mean understanding this
equation and how each line of its
formulation represents uh in terms of
the uh I mean trade-off between energy
entropy or complexity inaccuracy or
Divergence and evidence uh is key to
understanding almost everything in the
uh rest of the book and in many other
literature on active inference so
this is the perceptual part of active
inference so variation free energy
is a parameter that uh
uh is the notion that parameterizes the
surprisal of our perceptual information
we have about the external States
and then we'll see in the next section
uh the related and almost symmetrical
formulation to variation of free energy
namely expected free energy which is
basically the action part of the active
inference so we can see how those two uh
can somehow uh be seen as a kind of
unified formalism but described in the
alternate
Expressions so but another thing about
equation 2.5 is uh it it may be a bit
um I don't know daunting to see all the
relations between those three lines of
equation and how we can get from one to
the to the other so there are some
supplementary materials that we have
developed in the past weeks
which I think can help in clarifying how
the derivative nations of these three
lines of equation be done so I hope they
would be
clarifying in I mean and help to
understand how those three lines relate
to each other
uh so but the key Point here is uh
to understand the variation of free
energy is not something uh absolute but
it's just an upper Bound for the
minimization so as Daniel just uh
mentioned it's uh untractable to have
an absolute amount for the surprisal to
be minimized so we need to have an upper
bound uh in order to make that more
tractable because uh by Jane's
inequality as uh we'll saw in
um we chapter four I think
we can see that how the upper bound of
the surprisal uh
necessarily provides a condition for
minimizing the precise or the exact
um free the exact free energy
and that's the key Insight of equation
2.5 or the notion of variation of free
energy which is to provide this upper
bound instead of the exact amount of
surprises to be minimized
yeah what I'll what I'll add there is if
you knew exactly how well you should be
surprised by a given data point why then
you would have had the optimal model
however that is not tractable and so by
making a quantity that's always higher
or an upper bound the variational free
energy F which is a function of broadly
Q our beliefs or variational beliefs
which are built in a way that makes them
very compositional very optimizable very
interpretable and data
and we can reduce the Divergence here
the KL diversions with a double line
between Q our beliefs and P the kind of
actuality of it and if we can reduce
this Divergence in other words minimize
the free energy then we will come closer
and closer to the true surprise function
and do that in an attractable
incrementally optimizable way so
equation 2.5 is going to be the
variational free energy different ways
that it can be represented as it takes
in data and beliefs about the world Q
and then this is going to be expanded
into the future to include action with G
the expected free energy
now there's a lot more that we can say
about this there's a lot of
technicalities to go into but broadly
notice that g the expected free energy
is a functional of policy Pi because
it's only being evaluated to select
amongst different action outcomes pi and
another important difference is that
it's going to be describing sensory
outcomes that haven't yet happened a
sort of what would I perceive if I did a
or what if I did B and it's that kind of
comparison that allows the expected free
energy functional here
to be used in action selection or policy
selection as inference planning as
inference
that section is expanded upon
and in figure 2.6 we see a very nice
representation of the expected free
energy equation and then how when
certain aspects of this equation or
situation are zeroed out we get certain
other familiar cases for example
where there's no epistemic value there's
no information to learn then you get
ruthless expected utility Theory and
conversely where there is no pragmatic
value to extract so all outcomes are
equally valid or preferable then you get
things like Infomax principle and
optimal Bayesian design and then
everything in between is the space that
we're interested in and so this figure
2.6 shows that the expected free energy
functional can be seen as like a
generalization of a lot of other
settings related to perception and
action and planning amidst uncertainty
and section 2.9 closes the low road they
took us all the way to active inference
from Bayes theorem through the
generative model onto active inference
and clarifies these two Notions of
variational free energy that's the
real-time perceptual unfolding evidence
lower bound on surprisal tractable
optimizable and so on and f and g the
expected free energy which is able to do
planning as inference or policy
selection as inference expected free
energy is fundamentally prospective
and that enables counter factual
cognition
section 2.10 summarizes active inference
is a theory of how living artifacts
underwrite their existence by minimizing
surprise or attractable proxy to
surprise variational free energy via
perception and action and they motivate
that from a first principles base
theorem starting place
any closing thoughts on chapter 2 Ali
I would just humbly suggest for the
people who want to go through this
chapter to
try try their best to really understand
uh specifically what equation 2.5 and
2.6 represents and how uh I mean how to
use those equations to describe uh
different
situations with some missing elements as
well because I believe those sections
and particularly those equations are
absolutely essential to for
understanding everything active in
prints related both in this the rest of
this book and in the rest of the and in
almost all
thanks in just the last thought I'll
give on chapter two is this is exactly
the work that we do in the active
inference textbook group we really
welcome all backgrounds every single
question and uncertainty you have is
beautiful we have a lot of resources
that Ali and others make to make the
math approachable and rigorous
and natural language descriptions of the
equations and so on so yes it's really
important to understand the equations
because after all that's like the
skeleton that gives meaning to our usage
and fluency of the active inference
ontology which Ali and I are speaking
right now
we're not just saying surprise is
related to this because we felt it that
way it there is an underpinning and it
is a really interesting life's work to
explore it but we're finding ways to
communicate it and learn and teach it
better and better every time
so that's chapter two that's the low
road
moving on to chapter three the high road
to active inference and so recall that
the high road is like the why
so Ali please begin just go as long as
you want on through the high road to
octave inference
okay so the high road to active
inference uh begin with uh the question
um
about about the conditions for the
Persistence of code encode things I mean
uh what would we expect for a thing to
behave if it persists through time and
that's why sometimes fap is referred to
as the theory of every space thing and
it's not absolutely everything but thing
just in this sense of I mean persisting
through time and the notion that allows
for this
a thing to
act as it as it persists through time is
markup blankets so markup blanket is one
of the most uh essential ingredients of
the high road approach to active
inference and that's why this section
opens up with
um
describing how markup blanket allows to
describe the situation of interest uh
through this conceptual and mathematical
tool but one thing that I always point
out in almost all our all our textbook
cohorts is
uh in this section uh it it doesn't
um I mean uh exactly describe uh markup
blankets uh rigorously enough in terms
of uh it's carving up the
um I mean State space and so on so one
thing I uh I've I think is can be uh
clarifying in following uh all the
discussions around Marco blanket is to
keep in mind that it's just a boundary
in the state space so it's not a
necessarily spatial temporal boundary uh
although in many cases it manifests
itself as spatial temporal boundaries
such as the I don't know cell membranes
or organelle organelle membranes and so
on but it's not necessarily the case so
I think it it can be helpful to keep
that in mind when we every everywhere we
see markup blanket
uh but uh
in a very very simply markup blanket uh
is what allows for the agent or the
system to be statistically separated
from its environment as is shown here in
figure 3.1 so basically markup blanket
mathematically is just uh the uh I mean
the sensory and active States together
it consists of both of those States uh
and um it is statistically separates
what happened externally or internally
from each other so in other words
internal States cannot observe or infer
anything about the external States
directly but only through the markov's
Markov blanket and that's why it's
essential to
describe the systems in this way because
obviously in any sparse couple systems
there isn't a possibility to observe the
external States directly but only
through those sensory and active states
and one other thing that I also believe
can be a bit confusing in this picture
is that yes typo
in the active States and sensory States
because it's important to observe that
uh active state only or the flow in the
active States more precisely
only depends on internal and Market
States or blanket States and on the
other hand in sensory sensory states
only depend on
the external and blanket States so mu
and X in those two equations should be
exchanged uh yes yeah
let me just unpack into this before we
continue to add before we continue
yes so this is what's known as the
particular partition and that
terminology was brought to the fore by
Carl friston's famous monograph in 2019
and it's a little bit of a pun it's a
particular partition because this is
just one way to partition agent from
environment figure from ground
and we call what it partitions out the
blankets and internal States as the
particle so we can think about the most
inert least cognitive particle is like a
speck of dust doing Brownian diffusion
but also there are more sophisticated
kinds of cognitive particles that can
include
World models counterfactuals what would
happen if I did this all of those kinds
of sophisticated cognitive operations
that we can explore in active inference
so note the small typo that Ali
mentioned internal States and also these
edges reflect causal possibilities
amongst internal external and blanket
States blanket constituting the active U
and sensory y States
so these are map not territory this is
not a spatial temporal
articulation these are like causal maps
of the world that may have to do with
spatial temporal boundaries but are not
simply that
and sensory data or sensory States flow
onto internal States internal states are
involved in action selection resulting
in active states which have some causal
consequence in the world the generative
process the external states which
results in different sensory States
coming in again and so the Markov
blanket is what makes the internal and
the external States conditionally
independent and that can be thought of
as just a no telekinesis no telepathy
Clause the only way the information
comes across internal and external
states which are symmetrical with each
other is through the boundary or the
holographic screen or the Markov blanket
you can continue on Ali
uh okay so
the next section is
about surprise minimization and
self-evidency so again this term
self-evidencing is a common term and
active inference literature first
proposed by Jacob Howie so uh basically
it refers to how a system or agent or in
other words a particular State can
gather the evidence for itself
persistence or self-existence through
time in other words
by inferring the state of the
environment
and comparing
that inference with its internal States
or in other words with its generative
model
it it's basically a way I mean an
interpretation of that
um that kind of inference is uh on the
on the one hand there is this dynamical
interaction between the internal and
external state but we can somehow
interpret that uh physical Dynamics as
engaging in the active in the active
inference or as a model for
um the Persistence of the agent uh
through time so that's basically what it
refers to as self-evidencing and
then we go through the subsection 3.3.1
which is which sets the stage for the
recent formulation of active inference
uh as in mechanics which is to uh
somehow to to interpret the the active
surprise minimization
uh as minimizing the action through the
hamiltonian principle of least action
which is a variational principle uh and
by variational principle is what what is
meant here is just a computational or
mathematical tool that allows for the
computation or the derivative the I mean
specific derivations to happen so it's
not
uh identical to scientific theories or
scientific I don't know facts or
observations it's just a tool a
principle a mathematical tool so again
one of the main
misconceptions about free energy
principle is that it is on falsifiable
uh obviously if we see it in this way uh
it doesn't make sense to say that a
mathematical tool or principle is
unfalsifiable because it doesn't say
anything about the empirical evidence of
the phenomena we're talking about so
that's why here it's important to
understand how the surprise minimization
can be seen as this kind of variational
principle
and then
equation equation 3.1
draws the parallel between
the surprisal as defined in section in
chapter two sorry and this chapter so it
kind of ties up all the arguments
provided in the previous chapter with
this one and how everything comes
together in a single
formulation of active inference that but
they're just the two distinct approaches
to arrive at same destination
uh
uh and then we go also sorry the other
important
equation and again another key equation
here is equation 3.2
which is
a kind of EX sorry
yes equation I meant to say equation 3.2
not equation 3.1 sorry my bad so yes
the other section is about
the relations between inference
cognition and stochastic Dynamics as
I mean all the previous discussions
around
how the active inference can be seen as
a kind of self evidencing through the
variational
principles such as fep comes together to
do to
reframe the previous discussions we saw
in Chapter 2 about perception as
inference and action as inference and
to see the concepts of variational free
energy and expected free energy through
the lens of variational free energy a
variational
principle of least action so uh it the
unifies nicely all the material from uh
chapters two and three into
uh something that I mean not necessarily
distinct from each other but just two
sides of
awesome yeah I find table three one to
be very exciting it draws together
statistical physics Bayesian information
information Theory and cognitive
interpretations so it's kind of like
learn one thing learn many things
statistical physics has been talking
about minimization of variational free
energy for a long time and such methods
are absolutely everyday and
professionalized in Bayesian statistics
active inference is using exactly just
that to describe perception and action
and so on so that's very exciting
box 3.2 describes
free energy in statistical physics and
active inference I sometimes joke that
we have a few kinds of free energy we
have Tesla like
electrical power should be available to
everybody for no cost we're not talking
about that right now there's Gibbs free
energy which is the quantity that makes
chemical or thermochemical reactions
irreversible like the hydrolysis of ATP
and when we're talking about variational
free energy we're talking about an
information geometric space with similar
Dynamics similar kinetics and
thermodynamics but rather than
describing the reaction coordinates of a
chemical reaction we're thinking about
it in terms of Bayesian updating and
this is all called the Bayesian
mechanics
um 3.41 continues on with variational
free energy
3.42
goes into expected free energy so we see
this A Lot F
variational free energy that's the
real-time unfolding sensory flow
and then G expected free energy and the
policy planning as inference
section 3.5 concludes with a novel
Foundation Act of inference to
understand behavior and cognition
and it describes a few features of
active inference including its
distinguishing features from a few other
ways that people have looked at behavior
in cybernetics
section 3.6 goes into a bit more detail
on models policies and trajectories
having to do with agency and policy
selection
3.7 reconciliation of inactive
cybernetic and predictive theories under
active inference again the exact kind of
thing that there's a whole literature on
and it's always amazing to hear
everybody's perspective on in the
textbook groups
3 8 active inference from the emergence
of life to agency and three nine summary
you want to just give any other thoughts
that you have on chapter three
uh again it's one of the uh probably
most
fundamental chapters and
um uh I mean the topics covered in this
chapter is essential
are absolutely essential to understand
everything active in Prince related but
specifically the
discussions in sections
3.7 3.6 onward and again I believe uh is
really important to understand the
broader context of active inference and
how it relates to uh all the other
theories but specifically
section 3.8
provides a nice
view of how we can
use the same modeling to the same
theoretical tools to model both
non-living dynamical systems or sparse
couple dynamical stochastic systems and
also to
the systems that as agency or sentience
so it's a much broader theoretical
framework that doesn't restrict itself
to only particular kinds of systems or
agents
and we'll see much more elaboration on
that in the later
wonderful
all right that concludes our overview on
chapter three
now we're gonna skip to chapter six
so again this live stream is just
providing some materials on chapters one
two three and six eventually we're going
to get to all chapters and version them
and have as many of you as wants join
into the process of constructing these
but this is also that our textbook
groups can be really interactive and
people can show up having listened to
these background and context videos
all right so now we are in chapter six a
recipe for Designing active inference
models
Abraham Lincoln give me six hours to
chop down a tree and I will spend the
first four sharpening the ax
all right Ali what does the quote mean
and please lead us in to this discussion
uh okay so as the opening quotation
suggests it's about
uh honing the skill sets uh and a skill
set for applying active inference
framework to model uh the actual
empirical uh
situations that we want to we may use
active inference for and
it frames it as a four-step recipe to
actually didn't do the this kind of
model uh although it's turned as recipe
but uh I believe it's more like a
guideline and it's not like I don't know
cooking recipe that needs to be uh needs
to be observed uh strictly so
it's more like suggestions or guidelines
to uh to begin to apply active inference
framework in any kind of situation
we'd like so uh section 6.2 outlines
those four steps
so the first step is which system are we
modeling
in terms of how we can Define the market
blanket
that most effectively and efficient the
problem or question and we want to
explore through that modeling through
the modeling of that situation so uh
first step is about defining those
boundaries of
through markup blanket and the second
step is about what's the most
appropriate form for the generator model
because obviously we can have many
different types of generative models
depending on again what phenomena or
what questions we're trying to address
the third stage is how to set up the
generator model so after
settling upon the type of the general to
model we want to use
we can talk about the details of the
general to model and how it can be
efficiently modeled to be both tractable
and also
useful to address the situation of
interest and finally how to set up the
generative process so as we saw in
Chapter 2 there's a
important that slight distinction
between generative processing generative
model so they're not always the same but
they're closely related to each other
generative process to the hidden states
of the external world and generative
model is how the agent infer about those
hidden States
provided by generative process so uh
considering that the environment is
always very complex to be modeled
precisely and exactly with every
parameter accounted for we need to have
a restricted set of parameters to
account for in the generative process so
that's what stage four
deals for deals about so all of these
steps
even if not
observed or followed sequentially are
really
I mean essential to setting up I mean or
the initial setup of the situation we're
trying to model and uh
I cannot imagine how
any scenario can progress without
observing any of these
any of these steps at least uh I mean
just by thinking about how to set up the
situation or scenario
awesome uh and in the rest of the rest
of the chapter yes
just wanted to
um highlight again these steps don't
have to be followed in order they really
are like a summary as Mark has just
written in the live chat here it really
is like a summary of the earlier parts
of the book in terms of things that you
want to capture in your consideration
and also it's a great way to connect a
lot of the technical ideas that are
brought up about generative model
generative process and so on with some
bigger questions like who are we why are
we making this model how is the model
going to be used so we take that in a
lot of different ways in the textbook
groups but which system are we modeling
what is the most appropriate form for
the generative model
how should we set up the generative
model and how to set up the generative
process are all questions that must be
addressed at least when actually coming
through with carrying out a theoretical
or empirical octave inference modeling
task
and the following sections are going to
go into more detail on each of those
four questions so Ali do you want to go
for this 6'3 and carry on
okay so section
6613 is uh the elaboration of the first
step that we just saw uh which I mean
what systems are we modeling uh and um
by this question uh we mean how I mean
what kind of system uh
I mean how the system carves up the uh
State space using the markup blanket or
more precisely the active States and
sensory States and uh I believe it is
and
both one of the most fundamental and
also one of the probably one of the most
challenging steps uh to be carried out
because
well markup blanket is just a conceptual
tool we use to frame uh the natural
phenomena or any other scenario we want
to model so that scenario or that model
obviously doesn't care about how we set
up our markup blanket or how we need our
markup blanket but uh
deciding on a proper a set of active
States and sensory states that would
allow us to address the problems we need
to explore or the questions we need to
answer is not a trivial task and it
needs lots of lots of consideration and
even creativity on part of the
researcher or anyone who wants to design
an active inference based model for the
problem so that's where
the I mean the significance of doing
doing these kinds of modeling with the
insights and creativity of a
a researcher is I mean will be obvious
because it's not just something
mechanical or
despite the fact that
the word recipe uh
can somehow make us believe that it's
just a recipe to follow but in actuality
it's not the case at all so that's
uh
the discussion of a market blanket and
how what
criteria we need to keep in mind to
settle upon the proper
uh yeah proper markup blanket around our
system and the next section
what is the most appropriate for form
for the general to model so here again
we can have various
way to set up our generative model in
terms of whether it's discrete or
continuous variables we want to account
for
about the time scale is it shallow or
hierarchical
about uh or about the temporal depth of
the inference and planning so these are
all problems we need to
be precise about questions we need to
precise about whenever we want to set up
our generative
model
and then we go to section 6.5
how to set um sorry yeah how to set up
the generator model so after the
precisely describing what needs to be
accounted or what parameters and the
nature of the uh generative model uh
needs to be accounted for
uh then we will probably need to address
this question of how can that generative
model be actually set up so
setting up the variables for the
generative model will
I mean we will be concerned about how
those matrices as a b c and d matrices
matrices can be defined as we saw in
chapter four and then which parts of the
generative model are fixed and what is
learned so again it's really important
to know
what are the Dynamics of the of those
parameters are in terms of
the learning process and what what needs
to be updated consistently or learned as
opposed to the variables that
either don't require consistent updating
or they vary
quite slowly as compared to the time
scale of the generative model
and then we go
through the process of setting up the
generative process and as I mentioned
earlier it is probably one of the most
complicated
steps of the recipe because uh the
complexity the I mean the enormous
complexity of
any real-time situation
and particularly the environment that
the agent
will act and behave but
even if not having uh I mean even if
there is not any um
strict or I don't know obvious way to go
through the through this stage of
setting up the generator process this
section provides some helpful
criteria or helpful points in order to
help us
um
in that stage as well so finally
after going through all of these stages
we need to somehow get I mean obviously
we need results and we need to
provide our results in a we get our
results from our active inference model
and uh
section 6.7 addresses that
uh I mean the the very that very idea of
how to simulate visualize analyze and
fit data using active inference because
it's not just enough to set up the model
we need to get the model to work so how
can we feed the data into the model how
can we
read the data and finally how can we
analyze or analyze the simulated data
through the
active inference so this is
uh in a way
um a kind of preliminary recipe or
preliminary procedure for doing active
inference or an active inference
modeling or at least suggested way to to
do those kinds of modeling but in the
subsequent chapters in particular
chapters seven and eight will go through
some uh helpful cases studies for how to
actually use these procedures
um to model some real world situations
awesome thanks well there's a lot to say
on chapter six
one piece that comes up a lot is what is
in the active inference kernel the
cognitive kernel and what are situations
that we can model with active inference
there's a huge variety of cognitive
phenomena and statistical outcomes that
we might be interested to study like
counterfactuals and planning like
multi-scale attention and covert action
like the complex ways in which memories
might
um influence decision making in the
moment based upon associations made
between different sensory modalities
every amazing real world situation you
can imagine
and it's really helpful to think about
active inference as more like a
framework of
interoperable motifs that we can compose
and indeed even be creative with rather
than giving us all the answers at the
core model because the kind of essential
minimal active inference model doesn't
necessarily include every single
attribute that you might be interested
in just like any given linear regression
isn't going to include every single
feature that you're looking for this is
happening in a different type of
modeling framework but still there's a
lot of customization and development
that goes into adapting or elaborating
an active inference type model for your
given system or scenario of Interest
chapter 6 gives us some helpful
guidelines and things to consider which
we've unpacked and expanded on elsewhere
and in the textbook group we work
together to characterize different
systems of interest to map different
parts or different observables from that
system using the active inference
ontology into a unified active inference
type model so chapter six starts the
second half of the book which is the
more practice oriented part of the book
and the rest of the part two is going to
be a lot more about the specific kinds
of generative models that you can use
discrete and continuous time and about
using them with empirical data in
chapter nine but chapter six just stands
alone as a summary of part one of the
book in some ways and a set of four
questions which system or remodeling
what is the most appropriate form for
the generative model how to set up the
generative model and how to set up the
generative process so that we can be
active inference model ourselves
all right well Ollie thanks so much for
all of these great uh conversations and
cohorts
we will be able to process this video to
clip out these first versions of the
background and context overviews and
we'll distribute them to the cohorts so
that people can show up with their
Curiosities and passions and we'll see
where that goes any last thoughts
thank you it was a pleasure to go
through these chapters once again with
each time obviously with uh a bit more
understanding than than the previous one
so I'm looking forward to the next
cohorts
awesome all right thanks Ali farewell